#### MATTHIEU BLANKE

# **CURRICULUM VITAE**

### **ABOUT ME**

I am a PhD student in applied mathematics. I am passionate about complex systems, computer science and technology in general. I have a strong experience in programming. I am a hard worker and fast learner.



5 rue des Volubilis, 75013, Paris +33 6 11 31 69 12



matthieu.blanke@laposte.net



MB-29

#### **EDUCATION**

Paris, FRANCE 2020 - 2021

#### **ENS PARIS-SACLAY**

Master's degree MVA « Mathématiques, Vision, Apprentissage » Machine learning, statistics, optimal transport, optimization Minor in statistical Physics

Paris, FRANCE 2017 - 2021

# ÉCOLE POLYTECHNIQUE

Cycle ingénieur polytechnicien
Ranked 7th in the entrance exam
Applied mathematics, theoretical physics of

Applied mathematics, theoretical physics and computer science

Paris, FRANCE 2014 - 2017

# LYCÉE LOUIS-LE-GRAND

Classe préparatoire MPSI-MP\*

Mathematics, physics, computer science

Brest, FRANCE 2014 - 2017

### LYCÉE DE L'HARTELOIRE

Baccalauréat with major in mathematatics

Graduated with first class honours

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Paris, FRANCE September 2021 - now

#### INRIA Paris - PhD student

Deep implicit layers with applications to physical systems.

Supervised by Marc Lelarge in team DYOGENE.

Paris, FRANCE April 2021 - September 2021

# INRIA Paris – Research intern

Deep implicit layers with applications to physical systems.

Supervised by Marc Lelarge in team DYOGENE.

Paris, FRANCE April 2020 - August 2020

### ECONOPHYSIX - Research intern

Theoretical study of an econophysics market model. Developed a fully-fledged Python package for numerical simulations. Publication under review. Supervised by Michael Benzaquen and Jean-Philippe Bouchaud.

#### SAILDRONE – Platform Team intern

Developed data analysis Python modules for ocean physical measurements, including time series quality check and data pipeline engineering.

Normandy, FRANCE 2018

### MARINE NATIONALE – Military officer

Maritime security and law enforcement. Developed a Python data analysis tool for suspicious boats detection.

Paris, FRANCE 2017-2018

#### **ASSOCIATION X-TALENTS - Examiner**

Conducted weekly Mathematics and Physics oral tests preparing undergraduate students for the competitive entrance examinations of French Top Engineering Schools.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

under review

### Market impact in a multiple metaorder landscape

M. Blanke, J. Moran, P.-P. Crépin, J.-P. Bouchaud, M.Benzaquen, submitted to Journal of Statistical Mechanics.

#### PRESENTATIONS AND POSTERS

under review

# Differentiable planning for system identification

M. Blanke, M. Lelarge, submitted at NeurlPS workshop "Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences".

September 2021

## Deep learning isochronism

M. Blanke, CIRM Marseille, workshop "On Future Synergies for Stochastic and Learning Algorithms".

#### **PROJECTS**

Ongoing

Physics exercise book

Exercise book for undergraduate students preparing for the competitive exams for the top French

DNA sequence prediction using kernel methods

engineering schools. Éditions Ellipses.

Participation to the <u>Kaggle data challenge</u> of the course Machine learning with kernel methods of master's MVA.

Deep Latent Variable Models

Study of the exact likelihood of DLVMs, focusing on maximum likelihood estimation and missing data imputation, based on this paper. Supervised by S. Allassonnière.

Pattern recognition and Optimal Tranport

Optimal Transport and Wasserstein distances for signal processing and pattern recognition tasks, based on <a href="https://doi.org/10.2016/nat/2016/10.2016/nat/2016/

Hopfield Model

Theoretical analysis of the Hopfield model neural network. Python implementation and experiments. Supervised by L. Cualiandolo.

Market impact simulator

Fully-fledged Python module for noisy market impact experiments, confirming the theoretical results of the associated paper.

CycleGAN and anomaly detection

Image anomaly detection using the <u>cycleGAN</u> CNN architecture. Supervised by M. Lelarge.

2020

2020

2021

2021

2020

2020

2019

Image segmentation: Random Walker and SegNet Theoretical study and Python implementation of the Random Walker algorithm. Performance analysis versus the deep learning architecture SegNet. Supervised by S. Allassonnière.					2019
Machine Learning for household power consumption Clustering, pattern detection and statistics on weather from Météo France to predict energy consumption. Implemented the algorithms from scratch in C++.					
					2019
$X ext{-}Coin$ Developed a mobile app and programmed a Blockchain with Node.js for a new cryptocurrency.					2017
Physics study Theoretical study of wind waves. Programmed numerical simulations with Python.					
LANGUAGES					
FRENCH	ITALIAN	ENGLISH	GERMAN	SPANISH	
Fluent	Fluent	Fluent	Advanced	Beginner	

COMPUTER SKILLS

PROGRAMMING Python, Java, C, C++, Node.js, HTML, CSS

TYPESETTING

TeX